rather than
manually setting the hash values in our
contacts hash
one by one we want to populate the data
in that hash
by iterating over our contacts hash and
populating it with the appropriate data
i'm going to create one other array here
on line three
we'll call it fields and this list is
going to represent
the different data fields
the email address and phone number now
because we know we want to iterate over
our contacts hash
let's just begin by doing that
i'll invoke the each method
and our key value pairs will be passed
to the block as
arguments i'll define those parameters
as name and hash
and to start i'm just going to output
the name
and the hash
so when we run our code we see the name
which is the
key joe smith and the value which is an
empty hash
and our contacts hash only has that one
key value pair right now
so now that we can access the key in
value
we want to populate the value
with three of its own key value pairs
and we've already got
a list of the keys on line three in our
fields array
so what we can actually do is
iterate through our fields array as well
and we'll call our block parameter field
so within this block not only are the
key and value or the name and hash from
our contacts hash available
but also each field that we want to
populate that hash with
is also available to us so on line 7
we can simply assign
the key which will be each field
to an element from our contact data
array
now this array is a one-dimensional
array now
and it has three elements representing
the email address and phone number
so on our first iteration here we just
need
the first element of this contact data
array
now as the problem description indicated
there is a useful array method here that
we can use
and that is the shift method
i'm going to hop into irb so we can see
how this works
i'll copy our contact data array
and paste it into irb
now when i invoke the array shift method
on our array it returns the first
element of that array
which in this case is the email now an
important thing to note about this
method is that it is destructive
so not only does it return the first
element of the calling array
but it also removes it destructively
from that array
so now contact data only has
two elements
and i can invoke shift again
and now contact data has one element
so we can continue to do this until the
contact data array
is empty so this is going to be useful
in our program
as we iterate through and assign the
keys of this hash
we will call shift on our contact data
array
and this will allow us to remove and
return the first
element of the array repeatedly
so on line 11 i'm going to output
contacts
and at this point we would expect that
when our program finishes iterating
we have three key value pairs in the
hash
associated with the key joe smith so we
expect to see our email
address and phone number there
and that's what we see
now let's take a look at the bonus part
of this problem
i'm going to replace the contact data
array
with a two-dimensional contact data
this also contains information about
sally
and i'll add sally johnson to our
contacts hash as well
so the challenge is the same we want to
populate this
information into the hash values in our
contacts hash
but this time we're not just doing it
for a single person
our contact data array is now a two
dimensional array
so the main thing that changes here on
line eight
is how we tell our program which
element from the contact data array that
we want to use
if we simply call shift on the contact
data array as it is now
it will return the entire three element
subarray
instead we want to first access that
sub-array
and then invoke shift on the subarray
one way that we can do this is to use
the each with index method
to iterate through our contacts hash
now we'll have an additional block
parameter
we still pass the key in value which
we've called name and hash
but an index will also be passed into
our block
and this is going to work out just fine
for our purposes
because the contacts hash has two key
value pairs
and our contact data array has two
subarrays
now as we iterate through the
fields array and we assign each key as a
field in our hash we can reference
the contact data element at the
appropriate
index so we'll first iterate through the
fields array
assigning each key of our hash
to an element within the appropriate
contact data subarray
after we've gone through and populated
the first hash
then our index will increase and we'll
go through and populate that next hash
as well
let's output our contacts hash now and
we'll expect to see both hashes
associated with the keys joe smith and
sally johnson
populated with the appropriate data
and we do